Congress of Racial Equality (Syracuse Chapter) Collection
Congress of Racial Equality (Syracuse Chapter) Collection
1963-1965
Congress of Racial Equality. Syracuse Chapter.
0.5 linear ft. (SC)
Newsletters, publications, and mailings from the Syracuse Chapter.
149191
Biographical History
Formed in 1942, the Congress of Racial Equality (CORE) began as an organization committed to non-violent, interracial activism. As the Civil Rights movement gained momentum in the mid-20th century, CORE became a significant force in the African-American freedom movements. The organization used a variety of tactics such as sit-ins, pickets, and boycotts. By the 1960s, CORE became increasingly radical due to the influence of media attention and activists such as Malcolm X. CORE succeeded in playing a dominant role in the Civil Rights movement, but by the end of the 1960s the organization lost much of its national influence.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Congress of Racial Equality (Syracuse Chapter) Collection contains a variety of materials including newsletters, publications, and mailings from the Syracuse chapter of the organization.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is divided into five series: Correspondence, Photographs, Press releases, Printed materials, and Miscellaneous. The Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by recipient and Printed material is organized alphabetically by title. Meanwhile, Press releases are arranged chronologically.
Subject and Genre Headings
African Americans; Radicalism; Congress of Racial Equality. Syracuse Chapter.; Civil rights movements, New York (State), Syracuse.; Civil rights movements, Societies, etc.; Newsletters.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Outgoing Correspondence
    - Fellow Syracusan (Sc 233, Folder 1)
    - Friend, 2 letters (Sc 233, Folder 1)
    - Friend of Civil Rights (Sc 233, Folder 1)
    - Kharas, Ralph, 22 Jan 1964; undated; 2 letters; Mayor's Commission for Human Rights (Sc 233, Folder 1)
    - Reader (Sc 233, Folder 1)
    - Syracuse area clergyman (Sc 233, Folder 1)
- Photographs
  - Picket lines in downtown Syracuse (Missing 10/15/2008), negatives; 1 roll (Sc 233, Folder 1)
- Press releases
  - 1963-1965, undated (Sc 233, Folder 2)
- Printed materials
  - "Christmas 1963???" (Sc 233, Folder 3)
  - "Christmas 1963???: Where Are Their Voices?" (Sc 233, Folder 3)
  - "Chronology and Fact Sheet on the Events in the [Charles] Presley Case" (Sc 233, Folder 3)
  - "An Equal Time Replay: Leander Perez Replies" (Sc 233, Folder 3)
  - "An Equal Time Replay: Nils Douglas Replies" (Sc 233, Folder 3)
  - Freedom Carols: Join with Me (Sc 233, Folder 3)
  - Meeting notices, 2 notices (Sc 233, Folder 3)
  - "Niagara Mohawk [?illegible] Months After" (Sc 233, Folder 3)
  - Report of the Committee on Education of the Syracuse Area Council of the State Commission for Human Rights (Sc 233, Folder 3)
  - "Rules for Picket Line" (Sc 233, Folder 3)
  - Syracuse CORE Report on Police Procedures (Sc 233, Folder 3)
  - Upstate Manual: March on Albany, 10 Mar 1964 (Sc 233, Folder 3)
  - Published materials
    - All About Core (Sc 233, Folder 4)
    - In the Wind, Feb 1964; Apr 1964,; Aug 1964,; Dec 1964,; Apr 1965,; Dec 1965,; undated,; undated (Sc 233, Folder 4)
    - The Schools and Urban Renewal by Terry Ferrer (Sc 233, Folder 4)
    - Syracuse: How Far From Birmingham?, 2 copies (Sc 233, Folder 4)
    - Toward Social Justice: Project 101 (Sc 233, Folder 4)
    - Where is Democracy (Sc 233, Folder 4)
- Miscellaneous
  - undated, 3 items (Sc 233, Folder 5)